Why is the internet so insecure?
Primarily, because all of our software
infrastructure is written in unsafe
languages.
>> This is Simon Peyton Jones, co-creator
of the functional programming language
Haskell, and I asked him all about
programming language design.
>> If we rewrote all of our software
infrastructure in Rust, things would be
way, way better.
I think that statically typed languages
are huge boon for LLMs. I do large-scale
systematic refactorings fearlessly
because the type system keeps me safe.
In fact,
>> Would you recommend people learn how to
program today?
>> I think people have a right to be
worried in the sense that I think
there's going to be considerable
dislocation.
>> Here's the full episode.
I wanted to start by asking you, what is
functional programming in your words,
and why does it matter to people who
might use the other languages, the
imperative languages?
>> Functional programming is about
programming with values instead of
mutation. Um, so, uh, in a conventional
imperative programming, computation
proceeds by, um, like if I want to add
up the numbers between 1 and 100, um, I
have a a mutable cell containing a
running total, and then, as computation
proceeds, I keep adding, you know, I I I
I I keep adding to my running total. So,
there's a cell that changes its value
over time. Computation proceeds step by
step. There's a program counter.
Now, that's very unlike mathematics. If
I say 3 + 4 * 7, you don't think of a
mutable cell that changes its value over
time. You think, well, 3 + 4 is 7, 7 * 7
is 49. That just The answer is 49. So,
in a sense, it's more declarative than
imperative. Um, another way to think of
it is it's more like what a spreadsheet
does. In a spreadsheet formula, if you
put in a cell, you'd say,
in A1, you put the formula equals A2 *
A3 + 7,
well, then, that's just a formula that
is evaluated and you expect to compute
the values of A2 and A3 automatically
before computing A1. It wouldn't make
any sense
to compute A1 from the old values of A2
and A3, right? So, and there's no notion
of a program counter. There's no notion
of do this and then do that.
It wouldn't be sensible to say equals
print X plus three.
Because who knows when or even whether
that cell will ever that formula will
ever be evaluated. And then the surprise
is
that it is possible to do useful things
in such a limited language. When I would
learn programming, I learned it by
writing machine code in which the
fundamental mode of computation is
registers and program counters, right?
And mutation of registers as you go
along and memory. Like computation and
mutation seem to be inextricably
interwoven, right? That's how
computation gets done. Um so, it was a
surprise to me when I learned that well,
um it is possible to do useful things
with functional programs.
I still remember that amazing
revelation. Now, um
uh
In fact, one way to look at it is this.
Right back in the late 1920s, early
1930s,
Alan Turing was doing a PhD in Princeton
under the supervision of Alonzo Church.
Now, Alan Turing, as we all know,
invented the Turing machine, which is
fundamentally about mutation.
Right? It has a little tape and you you
can read things on the tape and then you
write back new things onto the tape and
it has an immutable program, right?
Now, Alonzo Church at the very same time
was working on something he called the
lambda calculus, in which there's no
notion of mutation. This is it the
lambda calculus is like the essence of
functional programming.
Programs execute just by reduction. Um
now, so these were two different models
of computation. You might ask, what can
you compute with the Turing machine and
what can can
with a lambda term. And the astonishing
thing that turned out, which is
completely non-obvious,
is that anything you compute with a
lambda term, you can compute with a
Turing machine, and anything you compute
with a Turing machine, you can compute
with lambda calculus.
So, that means that the two are
identical from the point of view of
their computational power.
Big surprise to me.
Okay, so they're equally powerful, and
then then the question is, um
you know, which which which might you
want to choose? As I say, I started life
from the my baseline of imperative
programming, and of course that's the
way you write programs, and functional
programming is a kind of weird,
anomalous, rather nerdy, academic thing.
But,
I became hooked on the idea that by
excluding side effects by default, that
is imperative programming has side
effects by default, by excluding side
effects by default, we could make
programs that are easier to write,
easier to maintain, easier to reason
about.
And then the question is, um
uh what are the practical obstacles? Is
it slower? Is it less convenient? And so
forth. So, in effect, I've devoted my
research life to exploring that
hypothesis. The wonderful thing about
being a researcher is you can take
something which at the time, this is
back in 19
back in 1980, uh functional programming
was very nerdy, geeky, academic, um but
I was allowed to
spend my professional life just saying,
"What would happen if you took that one
idea, programming with values,
and just ran with it? Where would you
get?"
Um and I think we've got somebody
somewhere pretty interesting. I don't
want to say that it's better
fundamentally, because after all, uh
Haskell on that journey started with
functional programming, then we learned
how to mix functional imperative
programming together in a way that we
might talk about later, right? So, it's
not really an either or, it's more of a
both and in the end.
But, my uh position now is, as often
say, when the limestone of imperative
programming is worn away, the granite of
functional programming will be revealed
underneath.
>> And why do you say that?
>> Well, functional programming is the
language of mathematics.
Right, that's that's how we
we fundamentally think about things when
we want to be formal. Indeed, if we want
to reason about and say what does this
imperative program do, we have to wheel
out a lot of mathematics and you know,
whole triples and so forth. But that's
all in the world of math, which is
functional programming.
Functional programming is just
mathematics brought to life and made
executable.
So,
you might wonder
I suppose um
you maybe saying, well, isn't imperative
programming just enough?
And I think that
there you have to have to um
uh just look at the broad sweep of
things. I think what's happened is that
from the world of functional
programming, lots of ideas have got
adopted into the imperative arena. Like
so they grew up over here in functional
programming
and then they have been adopted by the
imperative programming
things. So, you I think garbage
collection, you might think lambdas, you
might think language integrated query,
you might think about lots about type
systems,
polymorphism and static typing, tons of
that. So, at least it has been an
intellectually interesting experiment
that has been a very fertile laboratory
which to grow up ideas that can infect
the mainstream. Now,
um
my
instincts now is that we should start
from functional programming and do
imperative programming where necessary.
I think probably the mainstream is we
should start with imperative programming
and sort of add bits of functional
programming where possible.
But and I'm not going to say that
they're wrong to do that, just to say
that I think there's a pretty
interesting dialogue.
Um now,
you You to do have to think very
differently about the act of
programming, right? You do have to
rewire your brain quite a bit. Um but
just let me this is something we might
want to come back to. I said easier to
maintain.
As programs get old, well just think of
a 10-year-old program.
Right? If you have um a piece of
10-year-old code written by somebody
who's long since left your company that
mutates some more or less global
variables,
then you might be a little bit a bit a
little bit afraid about Oh, and there's
other bits of code scattered about that
also read or write those mutual those um
global variables, then you might be a
little cautious about making
modifications, right? Lest Oh, if I put
these two things if I do B and then A
instead of A and then B,
maybe,
you know, the global variable that I
read in read somewhere deep inside the
code is now not have the value that it
was expected to. So,
reading and writing um shared variables
that are visible, you know, outside the
scope sort of somewhat global variables
is a form of coupling between bits of
code that is very invisible.
Right? Very invisible. So, functional
programming forces that to become
visible.
It forces it into the open. And by the
act of forcing it into the open, that
strongly encourages a style of
programming which you would don't have
such interactions because they are
painful to manage.
Um so,
um it encourages a uh
uh a style in which programs execute in
modular box without interacting. Now,
every imperative programmer would want
to do that. But I want them to do that
in a provably secure way.
So, you can know that these programs
don't interact rather than just say,
"I've done my best."
>> Then I guess on the on the flip side
then, what are the downsides of
functional programming language?
>> Oh, well, it can be very tiresome and
inconvenient, right? So, you're
somewhere deep in the ball you know, a a
a subroutine of a subroutine of a
subroutine of a some soft software
stack, and you want to reach out and I
don't know, grab the time of day.
Oh dear.
That's a side effect.
But when in a pure functional language,
the time of and it did there's a good
reason because everybody else higher in
the stack is assuming that if I call
this function applied to, you know,
seven, it will give me the same answer
if I call it call it again applied to
seven. But if it can interrogate the
time of day, suddenly it might give a
different answer.
Right? So, this a simple a thing as look
as asking for the time of day
invalidates all set of assumptions and
so is not by default allowed at all. And
that can be a convenient because you all
you say, "Look guys, all I want to do is
get hold of the time of day. Don't give
me grief."
And so every functional programming
language including Haskell um provides
you with a little trapdoor.
Haskell's is called unsafePerformIO.
And it says,
"Trust me. I'm going to do something
that has side effects, but you can
pretend there weren't any."
All right. So, and it's called it is
literally spelled u n s a f e perform
i/o. It's the long name that has unsafe
in the title so that you the programmer
taking on the obligation to make sure
that what you're doing is okay.
Whereas in an imperative language,
everything you do could be
unsafePerformIO-ish.
>> [laughter]
>> I was watching one of your lectures and
you did go over a little bit the history
of functional programming languages
and you mentioned somewhere that there
was this idea of people building
hardware for functional programming
languages.
This just made me curious because I
didn't I only know the Von Neumann
architecture. Do you have any idea what
that might look like and some high-level
thoughts?
>> Well, I did it. Um and now I think it's
probably a bad idea.
Um but back in 19 when was Backus's
Turing Award lecture? I I it was 1978 or
there about.
What was it called? Um
>> Can programming be liberated from the
von Neumann style?
>> That's it. Now, he was saying two
things. Firstly,
he, the designer of Fortran, a
quintessentially imperative language,
the designer of Fortran was saying,
"Guys, we should do functional
programming."
That was the That was what the talk was
about. Um and um
uh
he introduced a language called FP
for functional programming. It was a
very particular, somewhat idiosyncratic
functional programming language, but
there was. So, that was rather amazing,
right? This was 1977.
Um
he was saying, "Guys, give up on
imperative programming. Just do
functional programming. Here's how you
do it."
But, he also said in the same lecture,
um
"We might imagine designing new hardware
to execute this new kind of language."
So, if you like, we've got Turing
machines, they let give rise to register
machines and microprocessors and so
forth. Maybe lambda calculus, perhaps if
we designed a machine from the ground up
to do lambda calculus,
it would look different.
So, that was of course very exciting.
And
um
uh similar kind of thinking led to an
actual commercial machine called the
Lisp machine. That was a piece of
hardware that was designed by Symbolics
to execute Lisp programs. Lisp is a
mostly functional programming language.
Um
And so, at the time I was, you know, in
my early 20s, we were thinking, "Oh,
crumbs, what would a piece of hardware
look like that could was primarily
designed to execute functional programs?
Would it have a different kind of
instruction set and architecture?" So,
um
the nearest we got to it actually was
although it was a big strand of work
then that was the um called the MIT data
flow project. So, data flow languages,
functional languages, they're definitely
the same kind of category, right? And
so, um
the MIT had this great group led by
Arvind called the MIT data flow group
and they designed in the end a machine
called monsoon.
It was specifically designed to execute
data flow programs, that is functional
programs.
It was based on uh you know a token
store and matching and tokens flowing
around and getting matched up and
executing. You can imagine data flowing
through a graph. When three arrives at a
plus node and four arrives at the other
input of the plus node, bam you can fire
that plus node, right? And that hardware
did all of that.
At a similar kind of time in England my
um
colleagues uh Thomas Clark, Joe Stoy and
others um built something called the SKI
machine, SKIM.
There's a paper about this in the
um uh FDC conference. And SKIM was
designed to execute SK combinators. So
at the time
David Turner has written a lovely paper
in which he described how to take lambda
calculus programs and translate them
into SK combinators. So you can read
about that in my book. It's a very
simple translation that you can give the
whole translation in half a dozen lines.
But um then you have this message of
this message of S's and K's. And S and K
reduction is very very easy.
Um so it's like the machine code of
functional program. That's one way to
think of it.
>> What is a SK combinator just for
context?
>> There are three combinators, SK and I.
So and they have simple reduction rules.
Here they are.
IX = X. KXY = X. SXYZ is X of Z applied
to Y of Z. End of story. That's all.
So it's very simple, right? So now all I
got to do is take to take my lambda
translate it into a giant tree of SK
combinators, right? S applied to K
applied to I of um
three and um S of Z of just a huge tree
of S's and K's.
Right? Now simply apply the rewrite
rules I gave you.
And you have That's That is program
execution.
It's rather astonishing that that can
execute arbitrarily complicated
programs, but it can.
Do you think that's rather amazing?
Now, then I can take an arbitrary
Haskell program, I can translate it into
lambda terms, and I can translate those
lambda terms into S and K, very simple
transformation, and I can just write
those Run those three rules, and it'll
produce the output of the Haskell
program. That's pretty amazing. And
indeed, there is an implementation of
Haskell that uses exactly this. It's
called microHS, and my colleague Lennart
Augustsson um has built it, and its
execution mechanism is SK combinator
reduction. And if you sit in microHS,
you can ask it to show you the S's and
K's that it produces. If we had a, you
know, shared screen, I could probably
show you. Um
Uh So, long story short then, um
uh
the SKI machine was designed to take SK
trees, big trees of S's and K
combinators, and just execute them
directly. So, it was built
in hardware, and it ran perfectly well,
um reasonably fast.
Now, why didn't this catch on? Why don't
we have
um functional programming machines? I
mean, at the time, it was a big idea. We
even had a conference called
Functional Programming Computer
Architecture, FPCA. It was right there
in the title of the conference.
But slowly, we became aware that
what was really happening is we were
doing at run time what we could do
instead at compile time.
And that is always a bad idea.
Imagine an interpreter for, I don't
know, um Pascal or something.
It'd be Or uh for Java. Like, we can
compile Java to bytecode, and we could
interpret the bytecode.
Right? So, then we are We're doing
something at run time. At run time, the
interpreter is looking at the bytecode
saying, dispatching to say which
instruction, blah blah blah. right?
Now, what does a JIT do? It takes a
sequence of bytecode and says, "Oh, no,
no.
I'm going to take that sequence of
bytecode and compile it to a sequence of
machine instructions that, when
executed, will do the same thing,
right?"
Much faster.
Because it can take advantage of common
of bytecode sequences, for example, to
say, you know, if you swap and then
swap, it's a no-op or something like
that, right?
So, what In fact, it turned out is this
whole SKI business, and any other And
indeed dataflow machines also, was
simply doing at runtime what you could
do better at compile time. We were
building an interpreter in hardware.
So, don't build the interpreter in
hardware. Instead, build a compiler
that translates
your lambda term into a sequence of
machine instructions that, when
executed,
will behave as if you had
done this uh reduction business.
And then you might think, well, machine
instructions for what machine?
Well,
from a practical point of view, it was
very hard to compete with Intel.
Right? They were just spending
Brazilians of man-years on making x86s
go faster.
And ARM likewise for ARMs. So, um we can
leverage all of that work by compiling
into their instruction set.
But even if you say you are God, you are
the chief executive in Intel, and can
tell them to add new instructions or
mechanisms to support functional
programming, what would you add?
Not very much.
Little bits to do with um
uh garbage collection barriers, I think.
And and such like, but nothing major.
So, in other words, I think the whole
build hardware to execute functional
programming directly turned out to be a
mistake. Inspiring mistake, fun mistake,
I had a great time, but a mistake.
It's better to build a compiler.
>> I would have thought there might be some
unique opportunities for parallelism
given the immutability in these
functional programming languages. So,
I Yeah, you described that that graph or
that SK combinator graph. I imagine you
could,
you know,
execute that all in parallel assuming
there's no connections across
the graph.
>> And indeed, that was the data flow
machine. The MIT data flow machine was
all based on that idea. It's saying just
throw the whole graph into the token
store and just run all the nodes that
are runnable.
Right?
But that's incredibly fine grained.
You've got to imagine this big tree of a
million nodes and your processor is sort
of wandering around over it doing little
things in parallel. There's a lot of
memory traffic going on there. And if
this these these little, you know,
threads have to, you know, are operating
on the same bit of tree, then the
synchronization costs,
um so, very, very fine grained computer
parallel computation like this turns out
to be impractical.
Like or not impractical. You could do
it, but it's very slow.
Right? So, the data flow people, their
history, if you look at the history of
the MIT data flow project, they started
with micro parallelism. Every individual
instruction was a separate parallel
computation that might take place and
the token store would match it up.
Right? And then they built more and more
compiler technology that grouped these
things together into larger units. So,
they expanded from micro threads of
single instruction threads into 10
instruction threads or 100 instruction
threads. Right?
But even that never really caught on.
So,
you're right, though,
that if I say in a Haskell program, E1 +
E2,
then I can do E1 and E2 in parallel. And
GHC does support you in doing that, but
you nowadays, rather than expecting the
compiler to do that automatically for
every sub-expression,
you can spark a computation. You say E1
par E2, and that says do E1 and E2 in
parallel. There's a project at Carnegie
Mellon
for a strict parallel strict language
called ML
that has a very good variant of parallel
ML going in a similar way. So,
essentially we've moved away from the
the dream of
automatically getting parallel at very,
very fine grain
to programmer
we give programmer clues about where
it's a good idea to do parallelism, but
um
uh and still the compiler will try not
to fork to too tiny grains.
>> I was searching on YouTube and I've
searched your name and this video came
up and it said "Haskell is useless,
Simon Peyton Jones."
>> [laughter]
>> And it's it's a video from a long time
ago. It's someone's got a low-quality
and a handheld camera. There's group of
researchers that are all talking. Butler
Lampson is across the table and it's
it's a fun little video. And in the
video, you lay out this two-dimensional
graph where on on one dimension
there is the useful versus useless axis
and then on the other dimension there is
the safe versus dangerous. And then
you're placing programming languages on
this two-dimensional graph and I think
you started by putting C as it's very
useful, but it's incredibly dangerous.
And then you put Haskell on the the
polar opposite side. It's You said it's
useless,
but it's very safe. What are the least
safe and most useful languages and why
do you place them there like C for
instance?
>> Well, yeah. So, um
let's see. In C, you program by
mutation. So,
it's unsafe in the sense that any
function can mutate any variable at any
time. It has a lot, you you pass
pointers around a lot and functions
mutate the memory pointed to by those
pointers. And moreover,
typically they can mutate it anywhere.
There's no array bounds checks or
anything. So, it's kind of like super
unsafe in the fact that this is
demonstrated by the fact Can you imagine
that that like all of these exploits
that we get every day, right? Um
that uh you know, MSRC is discovering in
huge numbers, but but we've had you
know,
why is the internet so insecure?
Primarily because all of our software
infrastructure is written in unsafe
languages. If we I mean
if we'd written all of our
you know, internet software and
operating systems in Haskell or maybe in
OCaml or ML,
99% of all these exploits would be
removed by construction.
Like it's like we've built a boat out of
paper clips and we're surprised that
it's leaky.
I mean, you shouldn't build boats out of
paper clips, right? Because they have
holes in them. You should build it out
of a secure substance, right? But then
it's too late. So, we spend incredible
amounts of human ingenuity and effort
patching the holes in our boat built of
paper clips. It's tragic. It's tragic
how much effort and ingenuity and money
has been lost and waste of resources
just because we wrote our um you know,
computational infrastructure for the
world in an insecure language. That's
what I mean by unsafe.
>> I mean, are there not vulnerabilities?
Like if I wrote something in Haskell, I
mean,
there's got to be some new type of
>> there are vulnerabilities. I just said
99%. I didn't say 100.
If I write a Haskell program that says,
"Receive message. If the message says,
'Tell me everything,' then spit out my
entire database in reply."
No language can stop you doing that,
right?
But, if you look at the program and it
doesn't have any such things,
right?
>> [laughter]
>> So, I mean
So, you know, nothing can prevent you
against high-level attacks to insecure
programs. Or, I mean, another example
might be deadlock, right? Two services,
no matter how securely written, if A
waits for B and B waits for A, deadlock.
Sorry.
No and no language is going to stop you
doing that.
Um you might hope for some high-level
verification tools.
But it's like
Surely, if you're trying to do something
hard, like prove that that doesn't
happen, you want to have a foundation
that is, you know, in which you've got
some bedrock to stand on. If you're
standing on sand and trying to prove
some advanced property, it's very, very
difficult. But, good point. I'm not
talking about 100% security. Absolutely
not. But, uh how many how many of how
many uh exploits are based on buffer
overruns?
Or, you know, pointer manipulation
that's gone wrong.
If you couldn't have a buffer overrun,
you couldn't do pointer manipulations
gone wrong. Those Those exploits just
wouldn't exist.
>> So, I mean, C is maybe half a century
old now.
Um
what about more modern versions of those
lower-level languages like Rust?
>> Much, much better. Much, much, much
better, right? If we rewrote all of our
software infrastructure in Rust,
things would be way, way better.
I I'm not actually even sure whether
Rust has array bounds checks built in,
but suppose it but it must have the
ability
>> to
>> uh
promise that you're not uh and actually
not bound. I don't quite know quite know
how, but if you compile all your code
with that switched on,
you're a way better situation. Way
better.
So, yes, this is not just functional
programming, but you did ask about why I
thought C was an insecure, unsafe
language.
>> [laughter]
>> If we imagine that graph, there's that
the upper right quadrant, which is
useful and safe. And you know, you
described that as Nirvana in the in in
the video. And I guess maybe over time,
I mean C's you know, somewhat really
unsafe, really useful.
>> Yes, so C I mean Rust has moved along
the axis
from
useful but very unsafe
to stay useful and become safer.
Now, Haskell started life as being very
safe but useless.
So, it's worth just you know, rehearsing
that because in the first version of
Haskell, there was no IO.
The only that a Haskell program was a
function of type string to string.
It's functional programming after all.
It could do no IO. All it could do was
take a string and produce a string.
So, obviously that's not very useful.
It's a little bit more useful. A
language that is very very safe
and completely useless is no-op
that does nothing ever.
Very safe
but very useless. Haskell was a bit
better, right? At least it lets you um
apply a function to a string and get
back another string.
So, of course we then worked on how
could we do IO in Haskell in a safe way.
That will lead to, you know, monads and
stuff. But But so, just as uh uh
the you know, we're moving from C
horizontally to go safer and safer
um but
uh but staying useful. So, from Haskell
we're moving sort of vertically to get
more and more useful without stopping
being safe.
And Nirvana is when we sort of meet up,
right? So, but the point is not to say
one is better than the other, but just
to say that we both seek things that are
useful and safe.
>> And when I think of functional languages
um in I guess in the mainstream or you
know, what people are kind of thinking
about, I hear Haskell. I also hear
OCaml. Uh how do these two programming
languages compare if someone was trying
to pick a functional language to work
with?
>> So, OCaml is um a strict language that
is called by value.
So, when you say F applied to 3 + 4,
it'll add 3 + 4 and then call F
to get 7, right? In Haskell, if you say
F of 3 + 4, it'll build a little
suspension that says, "Well, if you ever
need this 3 + 4,
you can evaluate it, but maybe you'll
never need it." And then it calls F.
That's a lazy language. Right? Now, uh
so because OCaml is strict, it has a
defined order of evaluation.
So if you say F of 3 + 4 and a second
parameter 8 + 9, it'll evaluate 3 + 4
and then 8 + 9 in that order.
Right? So it makes sense to say you can
say F of print hello,  print
goodbye.
Right? Because you'll get hello and then
goodbye printed.
So once you have a defined order of
evaluation, then it's pretty easy to
incorporate IO.
Right? Even though it's  a
functional language,
OCaml allows you to do IO without, you
know, without saying unsafe before my IO
or anything. In fact,
it has a defined order of evaluation and
it's perfectly kosher to do that.
As a sort of unintended consequence of
being called by value, it was also by
default impure. Now, good Haskell good
OCaml programmers won't use many side
effects, but
OCaml doesn't prevent you.
Haskell prevents you. Why does it
prevent you? Because if we'd allowed you
to say F of print hello,  print
goodbye,
those would be thunks, right? Not yet
evaluated.
Right? So if F happened to evaluate its
first argument and then its second,
we'd print hello and then goodbye. If it
evaluated its second and then its first,
we'd print goodbye and then hello. If it
didn't evaluate either, we wouldn't
print either of them.
That doesn't sound very good from a uh
you know, if you want to control what IO
is happening. Right? Laziness forced
Haskell to stay pure. Strictness allowed
OCaml, which grew out of the ML
tradition by the way, ML is another
functional language that predated
Haskell.
It was always strict and it always had
IO by default.
Um
it wasn't a goal, but that's just the
way it worked out. At the time, nobody
thought about it. It was just obvious.
So, that's a big difference between
OCaml and Haskell, right? Is that um
Now then, since then they've both grown
up. Haskell's gained sort of monads and
I uh OCaml has gained lots of uh lots of
fancy type systems. Some of them uh
Haskell and OCaml have learned from each
other. Um OCaml has gained an
interesting effect system recently and a
whole lot of new extensions. It's an
absolute hotbed of innovation at the
moment OCaml. So, I view OCaml and and
Haskell as kind of um siblings.
Um brothers and sisters, right? We love
each other, we learn from each other, um
we compete with each other, all of the
things that siblings do.
But, they're not the same, right? So,
siblings don't say, "I'm I'm just better
than you. You shouldn't exist." We say,
"Let's Let's enjoy our life together."
And that's what it That's the way it is.
>> You described the laziness and the
strict and as a programmer I my initial
thought is I would like to control the
order of execution. And when I say
print X, I and then print Y, I I want it
to happen that order, otherwise it would
be a little unintuitive. What is the
main benefit of laziness?
>> Why is laziness good? Well, um
uh John Hughes did did this rather well
way ago, 1980 something. He wrote a
program called Why Functional
Programming Matters.
Um
and one of its main thesis was that lazy
evaluation lets you um
uh compose programs in a particularly
modular way.
So, imagine a program that is I mean,
his classic example is a program that
plays chess,
right? So, one thing you could do is you
could imagine building a tree of all
possible moves starting from the
position we're at.
It would be a very, very big tree.
You know, OCaml, it would be too big.
Because first of all, I compute the
tree,
and then I'd start deciding what move to
do. I couldn't possibly do that. But if
the tree of all possible moves, you
know, has more nodes in it than the
number protons in the universe.
So, let's not do that. Now,
if instead you could build the tree Oh,
having got this tree, supposing you had
it, you could then walk over the tree
saying, "Ah, let me do some mini-maxing
and see Oh, this is looks like a good
Let me go this way." I could explore the
tree, right? Um
Now then, so
if you you know, OCaml, then you would
have to put the tree generation and the
tree exploration in one function.
Right? In Haskell, with lazy evaluation,
you can generate an infinite tree,
and then the explorer that prunes the
tree and explores just the bits of it
that is necessary is completely
modularly separated.
Right? I can build a different generator
and a different pruner. They're just
completely separate programs.
So, lazy evaluation is very powerful
glue that lets you glue together um
uh two programs that you'd like to be
distinct. Strict evaluation forces you
to merge them together.
>> Yeah, this reminds me I mean um
so, in Python, for instance, they have
the idea of a generator where
>> Yes.
>> you can lazily retrieve things.
>> Every strict language, every, you know,
serious strict language has lazy
evaluation in it. They're called
iterators or generators.
And so does OCaml.
All right?
But in Haskell, that's the default.
Now, instead in Haskell, so this is a
bit like Again, the two are converging
on the middle, right? Haskell, lazy by
default, but you can make things strict.
You can put in exclamation marks to say,
"Please evaluate this before the call."
All right?
Or the IO monad know how say evaluate,
but that's a a more brutal strict strict
annotation. So, in Haskell you can make
things stricter.
In OCaml you can make things lazier.
All right? So, it really boils down to
is what's the default.
We both want to have a mixture of the
two.
And then it becomes a bit cultural as to
which you prefer. Um
I I don't know. Uh some people sometimes
ask me, they say, "Well, if you were
designing Haskell again, would you make
it strict by default
with really good support for laziness?"
And I often say, "Well, I might."
Uh yeah, that seemed attractive because
frequently I found myself cursing
laziness as an implementer.
But, I strongly suspect that 10 years
after that I'd be thinking,
"Man, if only it was lazy by default."
Oh, when I say strict by default I would
or definitely mean strict but pure.
Like, no side effects.
>> A few times in our conversation you've
mentioned the word monad. And it seems
like it allows us to do the side effects
and
um
what is a monad and yeah, how does it
help us do side effects and preserve
ordering?
>> One
way to think about it that's very um
easy to understand and use is just to
imagine that the do notation is somehow
built into Haskell. So, you can say do
print X semicolon print Y.
And that has type
IO unit.
So,
a value of type IO unit means I do some
do some input output and return a value
of type unit.
An expression of type IO int
is an expression that when you run it
will do some
IO and return an int.
Okay? So, do let's you combine um
IO performing computations together. So,
uh
print three
has type
IO unit.
It does some IO,
namely printing three, um
get char
has type IO char. It does some IO,
namely reading a character from standard
input, and returns a character.
All right?
Notice that's different from just char.
So, you know,  x  that
has type char.
It's just a character pure, right?
Get char, the IO performing operation,
has type
IO char. It does some input output,
and returns a character. Okay.
The do notation lets you combine
together,
um
IO performing computations.
So, if you could say do,
and then you say x  get
char,
semicolon,
put char x,
then that x  get char, that
says run the get char computation,
and get me the character, call it x.
The put char x says
run the put char computation to put x,
and we combine them together with the do
notation, and it combines two
uh two computations to make one IO
performing computation.
Right?
So, but these things are completely
first class. That's what's new about
monads compared to just make it into
into C.
x  get char semicolon put
char x.
That's a computation whose type is IO
unit.
Right? Let me give it a name, so I can
say let foo
with type IO unit equals that do.
Now, I can pass foo as an argument to
something. I could put foo in a data
structure. I could return foo as a
result.
It's a value just as much as three
or plus.
In particular, for example, I could say,
"Do foo semicolon foo."
That takes foo, uses it twice. Each time
do foo semicolon foo says, "Do foo." and
then do foo again.
Right? So, I'll read a character and put
it and then read a character and put it
again.
So, these values of type IO T for some
type T are first-class values.
Right?
In C, I can't take X colon equals three
semicolon, you know, Y plus four
and pass that as an argument to
something and expect it to happen
wherever it's used, right? It's not a
first-class value.
>> When I first was learning this this
monad idea, it seems like you've you've
said in a few places it's a way to do
the side effects, but keeps the language
pure. But, when I saw it, my first
thought was it's almost like this little
you know, place where we segregate the
dirty things we want to do, I guess.
But, then how does that keep the
language pure?
>> Oh.
Because because I mean yeah, we are
lying here, but look, if your function
has type int to int, can it do any IO
any IO?
>> No.
If it has type int to IO int, it could
do arbitrary IO.
So, yes. So, it's nice pure int to int
function or dirty int to int function.
So, you might say, perhaps you're about
to say, that's a bit of a blunt
instrument.
Either completely pure or completely
dirty, right?
It gets you a awfully long way.
But, nevertheless, it would be cool if
you could um say, "Oh, I am a int to um
effectful
doing reading of files only int."
Right? So, you'd like to in the type
you'd like to say what kind of effects
can it have.
Can it throw exceptions?
Can it, you know, spawn new threads?
So, you'd like to enumerate the effects
this
computation could have, right? That
would be cool.
That's called an effect system.
And there's, you know, Brazilian
programming language papers about effect
systems. And it turns out that you can
indeed in the type system of Haskell
and indeed OCaml is is rapidly becoming
same. Uh you can express
just not just all or nothing, does it do
IO
game over
but rather
which particular effects does it do?
Including no effects at all, that's
pure.
Right?
A good place to start is a library
called Bluefin, which my um colleague
Tom Ellis has designed. It's a very nice
take on how to do effect systems in
Haskell.
>> I guess the purity comes from that this
is this this dirty stuff is signaled
through the type system. So
>> Correct.
>> Okay.
>> Correct. So, we can do it, but here it
is and be aware.
Yep. And because you have to thread, you
know, because the type system gets in
your face, you know, you you were trying
to
um
uh like map, say.
No.
Map says I apply a function to every
element of the list. Well, um
uh
so, it has type A to B to list of A to
list of B. If you were to apply an
IO-performing function, so it the
function you're applying has type like
int to IO of char
you could map that over a list, but you
just get a list of IO of chars.
That hasn't done any IO yet, right?
You want something that says, "Take a
list of IO chars and perform those
actions one at a time." So, I want a
function that goes type from type list
of IO char
to IO of list of char.
Right? And you might want to perform all
those actions
top to bottom, or maybe bottom to top.
Who knows? That's what this
function of type, you know, so yes, so
you could do it in various ways.
So, sometimes it gets in the way, right?
You say, "Oh, you know, can't I
just use map?"
>> [laughter]
>> Well, in Haskell, no, sorry.
You you're going to have to do a little
bit more work to tell me in what
sequence you want your effects to
happen.
Because by default, Haskell does not
specify sequence.
Um so,
the, you know, adding, uh, you know,
monads to control effects does get in
your face a bit.
And that's a that's the tax we pay. In
effect, that's part of the big
experiment that Haskell is doing is to
say, "Suppose we up front say we can
we're willing to pay that tax."
You know, how many followers can we get?
Uh, and the more but I'm I will note
that monads have infected quite a lot of
other languages, like F Sharp is
definitely a call by value impure
language, and yet F Sharp had these
workflows that were definitely monads,
right? Um,
and um,
monads have, you know, appeared in Scala
and in many other many other languages.
So, something that's very monad-like has
appeared lots elsewhere. It's been a
very unifying concept.
>> OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an ad product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSL, there's SCIM, there's RBAC,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast.
>> When I read [snorts] about Haskell and
people's perception of Haskell, one
thing that keeps coming up is that the
type system is really powerful. And so,
I kind of want to ask you maybe just
even on the highest level, what is a
type system in your words?
>> Okay, so what does a type system do? It
lets you reject silly programs
up front.
So, if I have a function that adds one
to things
and I apply it to a character or to an
IO computation
I'd like to that's going to fail at run
time.
All right? Because I can't add one to a
character. Or maybe you overload plus,
maybe I maybe I reverse reverse a list
or something. If I give If I've got a
list reverse I give it to somebody that
just isn't a list
then it's a bit silly to allow that and
only fail at run time.
So, fundamentally
type systems are about rejecting at
compile time programs that you do not
want to run because they will fail
at run time.
Okay.
Now
um we've had static type systems for a
long time um like uh you know, uh going
back to Pascal um and and earlier uh but
simple type systems are annoying because
they get in the way.
Imagine a function that reverses a list.
In Pascal, you could write a function
that reverses a list of integers.
But if you wanted to reverse a list of
characters
sorry
you can't that that function that
reverses a list of integers it has type
list of int list of int. So, you can't
apply it to a list of characters.
Game over.
You have to write another copy of the
code with a different type.
That's a bit annoying.
So, what are we going to do? We need
polymorphism. We need a more powerful
type system.
We want to give reverse the type for all
A
list of A to list of A. So, that up
front says, I work for any type A.
You give me a list of integers, fine.
I'll produce a list of integers. You
give me a list of characters, fine. I'll
produce a list of characters.
Notice that's much better than just list
to list.
I want to keep the fact there's a list
of integers, so I know if I apply, you
know, when I look inside of this, I know
I've got an integer.
Um but also, if I just list to list, I
might get back a a list of some
completely different type, but I know
that reverse returns a list with the
same type of things.
Right?
So, parametric polymorphism, super
valuable.
Right? If you want a static type system,
you must have parametric polymorphism.
The message is,
if your type system is too simple, it
gets in the way. Very important lesson,
because
it means that we cannot really say is a
type system useful or not unless we say
which one, because we know that
weak type systems are very inconvenient.
It must at least have parametric
polymorphism.
And that is another idea that was born
in the world of functional programming.
It was born in ML, incidentally, Robin
Milner's um
famous dictum, well-typed programs don't
go wrong. ML was a the first I think the
first parametrically polymorphic
function programming language, but
generics in Java and object-oriented
programming more generally is exactly
the same idea.
Right?
So, there's an idea that was born in
functional programming and made its way
into the mainstream.
>> And you mentioned polymorphism, and so
there's this parametric polymorphism in
the type system, but uh in the example
you mentioned where maybe you want to do
an operation on a list, and then the
type of the input changes. Uh I was
think just thinking what about when
people do polymorphism
in the classes?
>> Yeah, okay. But so now you're into a
whole more complicated world, right? So,
as soon as you say class, you're talking
static type system again, right? Um and
so object-oriented programming is is
another approach to polymorphism. So,
in an object-oriented language, we say
if we have a uh Ford that is a car and a
car is a vehicle,
then anything that works on vehicles
should also work on cars and should also
work on Fords.
So,
um the code that we write for cars works
unchanged
for
vehicles and for Fords.
Okay?
Now, that's a form of polymorphism. Not
parametric polymorphism, that's called
what you might call object-oriented
polymor- or subtype polymorphism.
Okay. So, now we but polymorphism in the
sense that the same code
the same executable code, actually the
same machine instructions, work on
values of different types.
Okay? In both cases.
Both reverse a list, same machine
instructions. Code that works on
vehicles works on uh things on Fords,
same machine instructions, right?
Okay.
That's what polymorphism in general
means. Parametric polymorphism means
this for all A, list of A's to list of
A's stuff.
Subtype polymorphism means if it works
on vehicles, it works on any subtype of
vehicles. Okay?
Now, the interaction of the two, which
you get by adding generics to an
object-oriented language,
is pretty complicated.
Oh, and by the way, adding side effects
as well.
And that's why you'll that that and uh
so
uh your question involving classes and
superclasses and so forth is smack in
that complicated world.
And I'm not sure it'll be very fruitful
for us to you know, we'd we'd we'd have
to get a lot more details of the type
system sorted out and know what to say.
Um but at this very high-level overview,
my my sort of the big point I'm trying
to make is weak type systems
get in the way. Type systems are meant
to reject programs that will go wrong,
but my function that reverses a list
of integers, it will also reverse the
list of characters. So, it's tiresome to
be told, "No, that is a bad program."
Right? I want to be able to write that
as that for a list of A to list of A.
So,
the idea of making type system more
complicated is to say uh programs that
you want to run, you can still write in
your static type system. Now, um you
might say, "Well, blimey, if that's all
if that's all, why don't we just get rid
of the static type system altogether?"
Now, we could run all of those programs,
but the trouble is you can run too many
programs now. You can run programs that
will crash at run time, and that's very,
very, very bad, and we all know
the costs of uh programs that that crash
at deployment that you could have
crashed before you even started to run
them, let alone before you even run your
first test.
Right?
Before you even linked it into an
executable,
that's really good. But, the biggest
benefit of a static type system, in my
humble opinion, is maintainability. If
you have a program written in um I don't
know, Pearl or Ruby,
um or um
Lisp in its inner basic form, um and it
was written 15 years ago, and the
original author has left, um and all of
the people who were involved at the time
it was written have left,
then that program is very difficult to
maintain.
And it it becomes almost immutable.
Nobody dares change it anymore. What
they do is it's an immutable piece of
software, and you do that stuff around
the edges to impedance match what you
really want to do to this now immutable
blob.
Now, of course, you have lots of tests.
So, test-driven development, I'm totally
with it. I love all any of all of that.
But,
still
GHC, for example, is itself written in
Haskell. It's 35 years old, and yet I do
large-scale systematic refactorings of
it,
you know,
fearlessly,
because the type system keeps me safe.
In fact, often what I'll do is I'll
change a few types and then start
compiling,
and then a sort of wave of changes
propagate through forced by, you know, I
just get type errors. So, I know what to
do.
Whereas the thought that I've changed
the representation of this data
structure a little bit, but I've added a
field to this data structure, where in
the entire compiler might that field be
read, written, or or freshly allocated?
I can't imagine how anybody maintains
30-year-old software and makes
large-scale changes like that
without a type system. It's
unimaginable. So, for me,
the benefit of type systems is
maintainability. Oh, and designability,
right? So, a type um I often write the
types of my programs up front. I write
the type, you know, the data types are
super perspicuous.
You know, if I say uh it's a bit like
writing the classes of a of an of an
object-oriented language, right? But, if
you have no types, no classes, nothing,
just, I don't know, S-expressions,
>> [laughter]
>> uh
types are the way I design language.
They're they're the way that I start
writing my designs.
>> I'm trying to understand uh other
mindset, like let's say C, for instance,
where I remember a lot of stuff when I
was learning it in college, for
instance,
uh many times where I I'd add a
character to a pointer or something, and
it it just works cuz
it interprets the character as a number.
Um and so, is there any value to having
that kind of type system, or is that
just strictly unredeemable?
>> Just use stronger.
I think there's no benefit to weaker.
>> Just off the top of my head, one thing I
think of is there is a set of programs
that will work but don't satisfy the
type system.
>> that's right.
>> That and but those are
I mean, I don't know if they're good.
That's subjective.
>> they may be good. So So So So uh uh that
like I like we started, if you have
Pascal
and you write a function to reverse a
list of integers, then if you apply it
to a list of characters, the same
machine instructions would work but it
is rejected, right?
So, we have rejected a perfectly decent
program, bad,
right? Our goal is to expand the
collection of the programs that satisfy
the type system
to include as many as possible of the
programs we want to run
without including any of the bad
programs that we don't want to run.
Okay?
Parametric polymorphism is a big step in
that direction.
Um other, you know, type system
innovations are a big step in that
direction, but there will always be some
programs
that would run perfectly well
that the type system rejects.
Imagine a tree that is um uh contains
integers at every node.
But
if you are 17 deep in the tree or 34 or
if you're in a multiple of 17 deep, the
integers can be characters instead. Or
the integers all turn out to be
characters, right?
Now,
you could write a program that generated
such trees and you could write a program
that consumed such trees knowing that
every 17th
um layer we switch to characters
but most static type systems would make
it pretty hard for you to accept that
program. And yet, it will run.
Now, you might say, "Oh, but I really
want to write that program, guys. You
know, don't get in my way." Well,
then
um
uh then we should provide a way for you
to bail out into dynamic typing.
Right?
What I'd like to do is to say, "Okay, so
if all else fails, then at least you
can, as it were, pair up a value with
its type representation." As one reason
we don't want to interpret an integer as
a double-precision float, for example,
is that, you know, they don't even have
the same representation, which is just
just nonsense. Right?
One possible way, which it untyped
languages let you do, is to tag every
integer and every double-precision float
with the fact, "I'm an integer. I'm a
double-precision float." But that has a
lot of overhead.
So, one merit, and it's not I think it's
not the biggest single merit, is a major
merit of static type systems, is you
have no tags.
You know that if it says it's an
integer, it's going to be an integer.
You know that if it's a double-precision
float, it's going to be double-precision
float. Right?
But if you're not sure, um maybe we
could make a way to make a pair of a
type representation and this value. The
type representation is now like a
runtime tag. It's like a little runtime
data structure that describes the type.
And then in your program, you could say,
"Now I want to say, uh I've got this
type dynamic. We'll call this pair a
value of type dynamic." Now, when I want
to take a value of type dynamic and
treat it as a character, we'll say, "Ah,
look Look at the type dynamic. See if it
says it's character. If it is, return
the character. If not, crash." Right?
Runtime failure.
That's fine. You can do that. So, um
and uh Haskell has good support for
dynamic typing where necessary. So, my
uh my my story would be static typing
should expand as as to carry as much as
possible.
And where you absolutely cannot do it,
sorry, then use dynamic typing, and
we'll provide facilities to support
that.
>> One thing I wanted to to talk with you
about is the compiler. How does the GHC
work on a on a high level?
>> So,
GHC takes a string like like any other
compiler that the source code of the
program, parses it.
Um and then it um
uh type checks it.
Because that is this a type correct
program.
Then it converts it to lambda calculus.
Now,
Haskell the Haskell AST, the original
source tree, has
50 different data types, 50 different
kinds of nodes, some of which have 30 or
40 different variants.
So, it's a really big, diverse,
complicated data structure.
The AST.
Lambda calculus has this
variant of the lambda calculus has
eight.
One to data type that maybe two or three
data types with eight constructors.
So, it's like taking a gigantic language
and squeezing it down into a tiny one.
And that tiny one we can then optimize,
right? That's the optimizer works on
that. So, the front end
does parse, rename, type check, desugar
into lambda calculus. That's the front
end.
The lambda calculus, particular
language, is called GHC's core language.
I'm quite proud of it cuz it's been very
very stable.
It's 35 years old and it has barely
changed since birth.
That's amazing, right? Because Haskell
has changed a lot, a lot.
Right? So, almost all of the innovation
in Haskell
has been in the front end.
Very little
in core.
Now, the back end, the core optimizer,
has changed a lot, too.
But all of the changes that were useful
there would have been useful 30 years
ago, right?
Yeah. So, they're two completely
separable things. So, I'm quite proud
about that. Core then we do a lot of
core-to-core passes that simply take
core program core program programs,
right? Lots and lots. Long pipeline.
Then we convert it um
uh to C-- which is a prototypical
imperative language. Think of it as a
portable assembly code.
Right? So, that bit is meant to be
platform independent.
So, it's simply that's the compiler that
take your program I said if you take
lambda calculus and compile it that's
that step, right? I want to compile the
lambda calculus into
you know, machine instructions really.
But I don't really mean machine instruc-
I mean portable machine instructions.
That's called C--
Then I want to convert C-- into actual
machine instructions for various
platforms. And then we could either do
that directly with a native code backend
or go via LLVM.
>> Interesting. I've never heard of C--
What Why not just go directly to I would
have thought maybe assembly or something
like that?
>> what happens in assembly in which for
which processor, please?
>> Oh, I see.
>> [laughter]
>> I guess it's the I would have thought
the lambda calculus part was already
portable. So, you just
>> It is, yeah. You could go straight but
but but so, there's work to go from
lambda calculus you could go all the way
to x86.
Then throw all that away and now go from
lambda calculus to pal PC.
Oh dear, I've just duplicated a lot of
work.
By going from lambda calculus to C-- and
then from C-- to x86 C-- We've set We've
We've avoided duplicating
the work that went from lambda calculus
to C-- right?
When you see it like that it's pretty
obvious, isn't it? Like you got to You
want to make the platform specific bit
as small as possible.
You would like to have as it were like a
generic architecture. One that can do
addition and has a program counter and a
stack and so forth.
That's all C-- just a portable assembly
language.
And then you say, "Oh, the nitty-gritty
of, you know, whether you have double
precision add and set the floating-point
bit here and there." That, well, that's
platform specific. The core is itself
statically typed. You know, but it's
always a surprising because no other
compiler does has this property, no
other production compiler.
By core statically typed, I don't just
mean that the initial the initial
program was type correct.
I mean that a core program, you can run
a type checker on that. And I might say,
"Why do you need to? Because after all,
if GHC is correct, it started with a
type correct core program
because it came from a type correct
Haskell program, assuming the desugaring
was right, and all the optimizations, if
they're right, will generate a type
correct core program. So, why do you
need to type check it?"
Answer:
to discover bugs in GHC.
Now, these are serious bugs, right? If
you ever take a type correct core
program and an optimization pass
produces a type incorrect
core program,
what will happen?
If we don't have the type checker for
core,
we'll generate machine code and we'll
run it and we'll get a seg fault.
Now, we have to backtrack for any
particular test program that now
crashes,
all the way to back up the pipeline, up
the pipeline, up the pipeline, up the
pipeline. Oh, it was this pass
of GHC that was faulty.
That's super hard to do because, you
know, you're getting out GDB on some
runtime failure
that is an indirect and perhaps distant
consequence
of the fact you just generated a type,
you know, you just made a you had a bug
in the optimizer.
So, it is amazing
to have a type checker for core.
Now,
why does nobody else do this? Well, it's
because their intermediate language,
typically, and this I really am talking
typically because I know of no other
compiler that has this property, none,
production compiler,
typically then they're, you know,
complex complex syntax trees decorated
with all sorts of pragmatic information
and things hanging on it onto it here
and there and
um
um you know, there's no there's no type
checker for it at all.
And there's no hope of one.
So, I'm very proud of the fact that core
is statically typed and I'm also also
think it's a
The most delightful thing is that the
way that it is statically typed it is a
It's an implementation of something
called system F.
So, system F when I said lambda calculus
lambda calculus as Alonzo Church had it
was untyped had no type system at all.
But Girard defined defined something
called system F which is a statically
typed lambda calculus a rather powerful
one. And core is essentially system F.
So, we literally adopted something from
the nerdy theoretical computer science
you know, logic community logic and
mathematics community and adopted it
directly in a in a production
implementation.
So,
I'm very proud of that.
Um I think core is
and the fact that we can do we have 35
years of worth of development that has
been not just not impeding but actively
aided by statically typed intermediate
language is really
a big marker in the ground.
>> You know, watching all your talks,
reading everything. One of the
interesting data points that you brought
up was that uh Haskell is talked about
more than used when you compared Stack
Overflow volume and you know, actually
GitHub volume. Like who's actually using
the programming language? Why do you
think that is?
>> So,
Haskell embodies one
key idea.
Immutability changes everything. There's
a quote from Pat Helland's talk that I
think you also paper which I think you
also looked at or read. Um So, it says
programming with values changes
everything about the way you think about
programming.
It's just
mind-changing. It's not necessarily
better, but it is different. And so,
Haskell takes that idea and runs with
it. Everything is driven by that one
idea. Everything else is incidental.
Uh in the early days, that meant we just
said, "Well, guys, suck it up, you know,
we'll keep um changing the language, and
if it breaks your programs, too bad." Um
so, it is, you know, a bit peculiar, and
therefore, um oh also, it felt a bit
academic, cuz initially, it was really
not very powerful. It was taking the key
idea, but you couldn't do very much with
it. We talked about that, right?
So, over time, GHC and on Haskell in in
general has become more and more
powerful. The type system has become
less and less in your way, and more and
more useful. The you know, all the
obstacles that make functional
programming harder become better. The
compiler generates faster code, it
compiles faster, and so forth. So, um
uh
So, it has become less, uh if you like,
peculiar. Um so, we've become more and
more taking into account the the um the
uh the needs of our users. But in a way,
the sort of cultural heritage is we
never give up on the one core principle.
We're just not going to give you
unrestricted side effects. Sorry.
Right?
You want to say I'm fully before I am,
and put up with the consequences. So,
we're going to stick to one core
principle, and then we'll we'll do lots
of work around the edges to make that
better. Right, so, um
that does limit our community somewhat,
right? It does mean you have to You
really have to think in a different way.
Immutability changes everything. That
means you'd have to think a different
way about about programming. Maybe you
don't want to think in a different way.
That's fine. Then don't use Haskell,
right? So, uh so, in a way, we've um we
we started from a very small user
community, uh very sort of pure and
nerdy one, and going going larger and
larger, but all slowly, slowly, but all
the time main- maintaining uh
faithfulness to this core principle.
>> I thought that was
very unique about Haskell, because I
feel a lot of the other programming
languages are user-centric. I mean, if
if people something, they work on it,
they add it. Whereas, Haskell feels more
principled or it's it's all starting
from these ideas. And if you don't
satisfy these ideas as a user, yeah,
well, we yeah, that's that's fine.
Um for instance, in one of your talks,
you mentioned somewhere that there was a
release of the compiler where if a file
wasn't type correct, then the compiler
would delete the file.
>> Oh, wait. It would report with the error
message first.
>> Yeah, it reports there. But, I thought
that was that was absurd. I mean, very
hostile, I guess, to the I mean, well,
it's it's if you're type safe, no
problems. But,
>> Oh, it was a mistake, right? It was a
bug. It wasn't deliberate.
>> [laughter]
>> And it only happened, you know, how did
the bug get, you know, get out? Because,
of course, if it always did that, we'd
have noticed.
Um how did it get into a release? Well,
it was because it was only on Windows
and only when you compile a module that
was not in the current directory.
But, at that stage, our um
our users were very forgiving. And, you
know, somebody wrote to us and said,
"Well, by the way, Simon, you might like
to know that, you know, GHC does this.
But, hey, don't worry about it, you
know, I just copy all my files somewhere
else before I compile and then I copy
them back."
So, of course, those days are long gone.
We pay a lot more attention to our users
and have much more rigorous CI testing
than ever we did, right? So, um
that's a that's a a story from a long
time ago, but it's a good cultural story
because it suggests that we've cared
about our users very much, but we we we
care about users who want in the in
their hearts want to be principled.
We're trying to appeal to One One of the
things I like best about Haskell is
people often say, "I just enjoy writing
Haskell."
Right? It's fun, right? My boss doesn't
allow me to because, you know, it
somehow doesn't fit with my production
shop. And And I but but for me, I would
go for I love writing this stuff every
time. Every time. Yeah,
that's that's very rewarding to me.
>> There's also this interesting, I don't
know if it's a cultural value, but it's
a statement that you say often in the
context of these older talks. You say
that you avoid success at all costs.
Could Could you explain what you mean by
that phrase?
>> Oh, yeah, this was just a little a
little play on words.
It was in a retrospective on Haskell I
gave as an invited talk at and um
Popple in a long time ago, probably 20
years ago. Uh so, it's a it's a little
play on words because it you can read it
as either avoid success at all costs.
And that's what we've been discussing.
Success at all costs means compromise
your principles in order to satisfy your
users or think that you're satisfying
users, you know, uh give them what they
say they want. Uh where more if we build
it, they will come kind of deal, right?
So,
avoid success at all costs. Or if you
parenthesize the other way, it says
avoid success
at all costs.
Or at all costs avoid success. And
that's saying uh that's a little joke,
but it says if you're too successful and
have too many users, it becomes more
difficult to make changes.
And we experience that right now. So, I
devote many many more of my personal
cycles to backward compati-
compatibility issues than ever I did.
I've devoted hundreds of uh you know, uh
hours and hours and well,
days and days, weeks and weeks in the
last year or two to the following what
seems to be a very simple property. If
if you can compile a program, a package,
in a whole program with GHC 10.0 and we
release GHC 10.2, you should be able to
compile that same package unchanged with
GHC 10.2.
Seems reasonable, right?
After all, 10.2 should just be better.
But, no.
GHC has never had that property.
And making it have that property has
turned out to be very, very
time-consuming. Previously, we just
never cared.
Then we started to care, but thought it
was a lot of work, and now we're
investing the work.
>> I guess that was from a long time ago. I
think nowadays, software engineering,
there's been a major shift in the last
year where a lot of code is being
generated by these models or these LLMs.
How do you see programming language
design shifting to accommodate a world
where a lot of the code is no longer
written by humans?
>> I think it may be the best thing that's
happened to statically typed languages
for a long time.
Because, as we've been discussing,
with a static type system, you cut down
the space of programs that the LLM can
generate.
Because it is perfectly capable of
running the compiler and saying, "Oh,
darn, that was a bad program. Better fix
it."
Right? So, a zillion iterations get done
behind the scenes.
Whereas in an untyped language, the
first one it coughed up, you'd have had
to run or run against its test suite, or
who knows what, but it's it drastically
tightens up that cycle.
Right?
So, I think that statically typed
languages are huge boon for LLMs.
Because it's too easy to
Programs are just strings, right? We
could um
They can just generate the next
plausible word, uh and you want you want
to make any implausible programs,
programs that really shouldn't run. You
want to make them not run right away.
Yeah.
>> If there's a slider on, I guess, the
strength of a type system, and you know,
the other side is weak. What what do you
see as the absolute strongest type
systems among programming languages?
>> Oh, Haskells, I think.
Haskell is exploring the bleeding edge.
There's an exception, which is that
module systems
are a um
and in particular sort of a functor
style module systems are explored much
more deeply in um the ML OCaml world.
And in the Haskell world we've
essentially never gone there. But
otherwise I think Haskell's right up
there. Now, of course, a language like
Scala
um
is also as the Scala has almost
everything Haskell has. I think not
quite. Um but it also has subtyping and
object oriented type object object
orientation. So that's a lot more
complicated, a lot more complicated I
think.
um
And they pay a price for it. I think
well, you know, Martin Odetsky would
agree that they pay a price for it. So
uh in complexity it's probably more
complicated than Haskell's.
um
Uh and maybe in terms of power. So maybe
I should have said Haskell and Scala are
the two lead Haskell, Scala, OCaml.
Perhaps I'll just put them in an
equivalence class for now. They're not
strictly comparable. They all have
things that we we in which they're more
powerful than the other probably.
>> What do you think are, you know, the
important problems to solve in the
future of programming languages today?
Maybe, you know, what are the unsolved
problems in the domain that are top of
mind for you?
>> I think it's actually hard to identify,
you know, to say here's a problem we
ought to solve, let's try to solve it.
But I think
another way to tackle is to say what are
interesting, you know, new languages out
there that are exploring very different
parts of the design space. And there I
think I do I do have a a candidate. So
um the language that is my day job,
right? I work for Epic and we're
designing a a programming language
called Verse.
Now Verse is a very exotic language.
It's it's really uh a functional logic
language. Um
So it's yet more expressive than
Haskell. It has a static type system but
a very different one to Haskell's. So if
you like uh the way I think of it is
like this. If you look at
um
uh C and Fortran, they look pretty
different if you're an imperative
programmer. But if you look at them, if
you zoom out so you can see functional
languages, then C and Fortran are pretty
close together.
Um you know, along with object-oriented
languages, they're all in a clump,
right? And then there's some functional
languages, you know, Haskell and ML and
OCaml and Scala out here. If you zoom
out still further,
then um the imperative languages and
functional languages are all together,
and Verse is way out here.
Right? So Verse is exploring a very new
point in the design space.
But just like functional programming
back in 1980,
it seems sufficiently interesting and
cool and unusual and weird that it's
worth exploring, right? So back in 1980,
nobody would said, "We're definitely
going to do functional programming, and
it's going to be useful for practical
applications." They said, "That's pretty
weird." Uh you know, by all means give
it a try, guys. And that's kind of where
I'm with Verse. Um Uh one difference is
that back in 1980, we were purely
academics. And now but Verse is being
developed by well, Epic Games.
Um so we've got some, you know, much
more muscle behind it um than um
uh you know, was behind functional
programming to begin with. So we'll see.
It's a very interesting intellectual
endeavor.
Adventure, I should say.
>> Yeah, I think a lot of people, like
students, they may be worried about AI
or you know, studying computer science.
Would you recommend people learn how to
program today given that AI is uh
starting to write reasonable code now?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. So I think people are
right to be worried in the sense that I
think there's going to be considerable
dislocation.
Right?
It's like, you know,
if you were in the industrial
revolution, then lots of people lost
their jobs as, you know, spinners and
weavers. Um
and it wasn't easy for them to get a new
job in the new economy. Now, the new
economy had in the end had more jobs,
but
there was if you were one of the people
who just lost their job, that was not a
happy place to be.
From our perspective, you know, Olympian
perspective of a few hundred years
later, we think, well, it's just a blip,
right? If you're part of the blip,
problem, right? So, I think they're
right to be worried.
Um we don't know how things will shake
out. I'm actually optimistic that in the
medium term, if we don't, you know,
destroy ourselves with some truly
existential thing, but from an
employment market point of view, I'm
optimistic that in the end, you know,
we'll just be in a higher place that AIs
will just be a
a bigger power tool. I mean,
everyone, we like using compilers,
right? We don't like machine code
anymore. Compilers make us more
productive. Maybe LLMs can make us more
productive. That's what I hope. I sort
of believe modulo dislocation effects.
Now,
um
should we
teach children or even undergraduates
how to program? So, I think still yes.
Um
um the reason is because
um
uh like one way to say it is co-pilots
need pilots.
Right? I think co-pilot is quite a good
title that Microsoft gave their tools,
right? Because it encourages you to
believe it's your partner, not your
boss.
Um
if LLMs spit out a pile of goop, and we
literally do not understand what it
does, we just try it and it kind of
works,
that might be okay if we're just
throwing up a quick visualization. It
might be less okay if the quick
visualization is going to drive our
policy um choices about as a nation
whether to go into lockdown because of
COVID, um or if this program is going to
run my airplane or train signaling
system.
So, now those are, you know, extreme
ends of the spectrum, you know, from
quick and dirty things it really doesn't
matter if it doesn't work, uh
but it kind of does a lot of the time,
absolutely fine, to
this is a 30-year code base, it's going
to last a long time. I really want to
make sure that it like putting new stuff
into GHC. If somebody sends me a pile of
AI-generated code to put into GHC, I'm
not going to put it in. Unless I've
reviewed it, or somebody's reviewed it,
because in 10 years time, I'm going to
want to change that code. How do I even
know what it does? If it's simply a
magic incantation that somebody's done
that kind of worked on the test they
did, but maybe won't work in deployment,
that's no good. So,
I really want
uh long-lived maintainable code to be
well reviewed. Sorry. Um so, and to do
that, I need reviewers who can write
code, who know
Um let me mention one other
perspective. Um
If you think about what every child
should know,
um
when I um
uh think about whatever a child should
know about computing, I would include
binary and bits.
Not Oh, just as for physics, I would
include atoms and molecules.
Now, it's not that in real life anybody
manipulates atoms or molecules, or takes
decisions which are based directly on
their knowledge of atom knowledge, but
somehow knowledge that all matter is
made up of atoms.
You know, constituted of a finite number
of elements that atoms could block
together with. That knowledge underpins
everything we understand about the
natural world. If you literally have
never been told that,
you are sort of emasculated
as a even as a citizen, let alone as a
scientist. So,
if you literally do not know that
everything is composed of bits, that
words and music and text and LLMs and
everything's all just bits,
I think you're crippled.
So, I want every child to learn uh you
know, it's like I want you to learn the
bottom that they It's It's all bits,
nothing else. It's all just bits.
I give a talk. The talk is called Bits
with Soul.
Um they're easy to grab for. It's a talk
I gave to an audience that was not
computer science audience at all. It was
a completely lay audience, ranging from
14-year-olds to professors of quantum
mechanics. Pretty difficult audience to
address. Um and it was meant to be about
um
all about uh codes and coding and bits.
So, um,
and so it tries to get at the essence of
why why do I think it's important that
every every child, every person, every
human being should understand something
about the computational universe that
surrounds them. And that's founded in
bits. Now, just to to develop the
analogy a bit further, I would then say,
"And it also, I think I want them to
also know about programming programs. I
want them to know that computers
fundamentally execute by following
machine instructions blindly. Right?
There is not magic. It's not hocus
pocus. It's just remorseless and very
dumb.
Right? It's incredibly empowering then.
Um,
and also to learn the basics about how
neural networks work. In the same talk,
I explain how a a one neuron neural
network works.
Um,
and that's enough. Uh, then then it's
actually true to say, not distorting the
facts to say, "Chat GPT is just a
trillion of those
wired together."
Um, and astonishingly, that very simple
So, so all Chat GPT is is
a trillion floating point numbers and a
lot of floating point arithmetic.
That helps you to make sense of a
question like,
"Can Chat GPT have feelings?"
Well,
it gives you
a I mean, of course that's a
philosophical question, but informs
your, you know, your discussion about it
if you know that all it is
is trillion floats and a lot of floating
point arithmetic. That's all. Nothing
more.
Anyway, sorry, long answer to your
question. But, so I I So, yes, basic
programming, absolutely. Yeah. Becoming
very skilled in how to use, you know,
web Django framework 2.7, maybe not so
much.
Maybe. I think one thing that LLMs are
very good at is knowing the arcane and
complicated APIs that many of these
frameworks present. When you There's
just, you know, 10,000 functions you've
got to know, and if an LLM's really good
at knowing that, I don't want to learn
them.
>> You mentioned somewhere someone asked
you, you know, what's your favorite
programming language? And obviously
Haskell's got to be number one.
>> Yeah.
>> But for your second favorite programming
language, you said it was Excel.
At that time, why was Excel your
favorite programming language?
>> Oh, because it's the world's most widely
used functional programming language.
The formula language is a functional
language, isn't it?
Doesn't have any side effects. You
program entirely with values.
So, the formula language of Excel is
a functional programming language, a
very weak one.
It doesn't even let you define new
functions.
And it has a very limited collection of
data types,
namely just, you know, flat arrays and
numbers and strings.
So,
when I was working for Microsoft, I took
it as my
uh my uh what's the word? Uh
um war cry to say, "Let's take that
idea. Excel is the world's most widely
used functional language by three orders
of magnitude."
And oh, not it's the world's most widely
used programming language by three
orders of magnitude, not just functional
language.
Excel is used by many, many more
programmers, users, domain experts than
any any imperative language.
Right?
Imperative language has a few million
users.
Excel, hundreds of millions of users,
right?
Even if you just restricted users who
are using formulae.
So, how can we delight those users?
Answer, take ideas from functional
programming and use them to make Excel's
formula language more powerful.
It took me 20 years, but Excel did
finally add lambda to Excel.
Look it up. There are blog posts about
it and and many YouTube videos about it.
So, you can now program in Excel using
full lambda as Alonzo Church originally
defined it.
You can write anything like because it
lambda is computationally complete. You
can write any computation in Excel now.
It would be a bit slow, but you can.
And much more practically, you can take
formulae that previously you just copy
pasted here and there
and you wanted to make reusable, wrap
them up in a lambda and now you can just
call the lambda.
And now, it is a proper grown-up
functional language that is Turing
complete.
Just search for lambda Excel. Those two
keywords will get you lots of raw
material.
>> Last question for you is knowing
everything that you know now from your
career, if you could go back to when you
just graduated from college and give
yourself some advice, what would you
say?
>> All of these people who you see very
successful wandering around looking as
if they made it. I guess you might class
me among them now. Um Uh
they are all of them just making it up
as they go along.
They feel insecure, uncertain, not sure
what to do next, um not sure of what
their next steps are, not sure of what
next problem they're going to tackle,
unsure about whether they what they're
doing is going to be successful or not.
Um and so, all of their confidence is I
mean they project confidence maybe.
That's partly a life skill. Um
but often they're not. Um
and so, the fact that, you know, in my
in those days, of course, I felt very
not confident. I would say, you know,
since all of these um successful people
are making it up as they go along, it
it's fine for you to be as well.
Um
And they've been lucky, moreover.
They've been lucky. Uh they've had some
uh
but if you want to be lucky,
you do need to put yourself in a
position where uh
accidents can happen to you.
And that means taking risks. So, if you
want to be lucky, you need to be in a
put yourself in positions where lucky
things could happen.
Right. Um and that means taking some
kind of risk. So, if you're very
conservative and have to take any risk,
then it's very unlikely that the
accident that is life-transforming will
happen. That's a balance, of course. Um
but it means that accidents are not so
bad. And of course,
um dying is bad, but
lots of accidents may change your life
in in in a way that might be surprising
to you, but turns out to be not so bad
in when retrospect.
>> Awesome. Well, yeah, thank you so much
for your time. I really appreciate it,
Professor Jones.
>> We will let you know if that's okay with
you. Uh thanks. Bye.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebreaker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides. Um
this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so, if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the
podcast, and I'll see you in the next
episode.